howdy this is jim rutt and this is the
jim rutt show
[Music]
listeners have asked us to provide
pointers some of the resources we talk
about on the show
we now have links to books and articles
referenced in recent podcasts that are
available on our website
we also offer full transcripts go to
jimrutshow.com
that's jimrutsshow.com
today's guest is rachel haywire she's a
writer
entrepreneur musician event producer and
model hi good to be here jim
yeah good to have you here i did my
research as i always do before i have a
guest on the
podcast and you have a interesting and
highly varied background
rachel's the author of the new art write
and accedizia if i pronounce that
correctly
and a couple of other things that she's
associated with she's now blogging
as the cultural futurist at
rachelhaywire.substack.com
i actually subscribe to it look pretty
interesting to me and if we don't want
the
advertising driven behemoths like
facebook
to dominate our discourse we got to be
prepared to lay a few pennies out to
support the
interesting writers in the world she's
also got
a new event coming up called the elixir
salon which will be on june 27th
you can get details on elixir salon.net
and here's one i was amazed i had no
idea until i started doing my digging
she ran for president of the united
states for the nomination
of the transhumanist party and guess
what she came in second
you know she got 31 percent of the vote
and now here's a real hilarious one
the person that beat her has just been
expelled from the transhumanist party
for
can you believe this can we top this for
craziness claiming that he's going to
grow
his own human cells for meat consumption
he's been kicked out of the
transhumanist party for
uh cannibalism amongst other things it's
too ridiculous and i actually i had so
many people that voted for me
i had a huge populist support base i'm
more than i don't consider myself a
populist in the wider political sphere i
do consider myself
a populist in the transhumanist sphere
and i had so many people
that were working on my campaign but
apparently like some elitist oligarchs
at the top they were a little upset
that i was not the right public
relations
person um all i can say is i might be a
little out there but i am not a cannibal
so i would have been better pr than that
guy um and i actually i don't even refer
to myself as a transgenist anymore i
call myself a futurist
i feel like transhumanism is mostly just
focused on immortality where my interest
is
more cybernetics artificial intelligence
virtual reality um just like extending
human capacity um
and i think uh the life extension sector
of transhumanism has become like just
another facet of public health
and i really don't feel like it's a a
movement that is going to grow
because they're just trying to you know
get in with the public
health community and i'm like no we
should be building incredible things
with technology so
definitely a difference of vision yeah
well now well since you came in second
now that the cannibal has been booted do
you become the nominee
i don't think that i would do anything
transgenders related again
i'm not interested in the united states
transunionist party
i'm interested in building my new
company throwing elixir salon
and i like a lot about independent
candidates and i think that
you know maybe i would help them with
their campaign and maybe run
independently or
even as a libertarian in the future so
um yeah who knows what the future holds
right
absolutely so you mentioned uh and i
mentioned the elixir salon coming up on
june 27th why don't you tell us a little
bit about that
so elixir salon is my baby when
krogan 19 hit it seemed like socializing
with people
like just on these zoom calls it really
wasn't doing anything for me
you know i mean it was cool to have
meetings with friends who i haven't seen
in a while
catch up talk about cover 19 um but
people
really just weren't having fun um the
first time i had
fun at an online event was when i
started going to the
stoa to go to those events and i
remember talking had
with alexander bard peter limberg and
colin zion
and we had talked about new potential
for what we could do like in this this
current time of serious distancing
and i believe it was peter lindberg who
said rachel you should throw like
the online burning man and at first i
was like nah because burning man isn't
what it used to be
um but the general sentiment of getting
together
creative people free thinkers artists
and dancers and i
thought you know philosophers right if
all things philosophy is the most
important thing right now to me
i think we should do this i think we
should make it happen so peter inspired
me
and i decided to throw the elixir salon
and bring together philosophers
architects
bring some musicians on board even poets
we have a
noise artist an industrial musician
everybody from robin hansen
to peter lindbergh himself we have nana
power
she is a philosopher and writer in the
uk miss metaverse a futurist and we even
have zach voorhees the google
whistleblower
so we've got a really great lineup and
it's going to be happening
on saturday at 7 00 pm
and we are accepting donations even
though the event is free
and donating 20 of our donations to
maps because they're working on finding
a cure for ptsd
using mdma and as someone who knows
how hard ptsd is and someone who knows
how great mdma
works for ptsd i think it is criminal
that
it is illegal you know so i really love
the work that max is doing
it's in the direction of helping people
that have trauma making people's lives
better
and we're really happy to be in this
collaboration yep that sounds
interesting
let's go on to the next thing one of the
articles in your new uh cultural
futurist is called pulling out of the
narrative
uh and it talks a little bit a little
bit about the crazy narrative on all
sides of us and you list a number of
interesting things you do besides
getting engaged
what do you tell the audience a little
bit about what you mean by pulling out
of the narrative what is the narrative
and why should we pull out of it well
the narrative
is what some people would refer to as
the matrix the stimulation
the series of news articles that keep
people outraged
or simply like being in the middle of a
hornet's nest
you know um you have all of these
stories coming out about
everybody's take on events that they
weren't even there for
everybody has an agenda and people feel
like they need to participate and like
you know take a position for somebody's
agenda themselves and it doesn't really
make a lot of sense
because the narrative it's not
interested in you you know the narrative
isn't interested in you and every time
that you comment on a an article
every time you state your opinion about
an issue you
you're just wasting your time what you
should be doing is creating things and
not participating
in this circus so the the surface the
simulation the matrix the narrative
yeah it's uh it's certainly a bizarre
the the narrative out there
and it's uh you know a mixture of
craziness bad
faith uh bad information and then
sprinkled here and there the occasional
gem
yeah yeah and the occasional gem is
usually found outside of the narrative
yeah at least outside of the the
mainstream narrative you know
truthfully i don't even go on facebook
in general anymore other than some
specialty groups i'm a member of
and twitter i have to curate my list
very carefully
or you're back in the middle of the
narrative so i understand exactly what
you're saying
so what would you suggest people do
instead what are some other ways to
spend that energy particularly here that
were still a lot of us
uh locked up under uh covet 19
lockdown well i know you're big on game
b is that the
is that your turn by the way did you
create the term game b no
though i was there at the founding the
person who created the term game b
was probably jordan hall and the person
who decided that it would be the a good
brand
for a social movement was thor muller
it was part of a group of us that were
meeting every six weeks face to face to
create the future that's what we were
doing and
those people that are interested in game
b can go to the game b group on facebook
uh where there's a few thousand people
talking about it
definitely a happening thing trying to
get us out of the current
basin of attraction where our society
seems to be stuck
not only is it stuck but it's on a
self-terminating trajectory and it's
going to die
if something isn't done and we're
working on what needs to be done
yeah that's certainly one way to pull
out of the narrative to create a game b
then you have your own narrative going
on and you're not so much
you're not focused on celebrities you're
not focused on journalist
drama you know i don't care about what
somebody said at the new york times i
don't
care if it's the left or the right
complaining i know i'm never going to
get a job at the new york times so i
don't care what happens there
i'm not interested in things that have
no relevance to my life
because i mean who has time for that yep
absolutely let's go on to uh three your
tweets which i found
interesting and i think you know
actually follow on this theme in fact
your pin tweet
is this find your people do not worry
about who is the center of influence
who is going to bring you power find
people you connect and work well with
find people who share your visions
ignore the noise
and rebuild civilization couldn't said
it better myself now
then your next one which i liked was
knew a guy who would never build
anything he was even afraid to go to the
store without strategizing
and accused anyone was skinning the game
of being a pawn
as others built empires and towers he
built an environment of paranoia on his
discord server then finally if we call
everyone who takes themselves seriously
a narcissist
shaming them into turning themselves
into a clown
don't we just have a village of idiots i
love it thank you
i'm glad that you appreciated that so
where do you come where are you coming
from on that i mean what is that what is
the center of your ethos that causes you
to say those three things uh
probably in the first ten tweets that i
came upon well let's start with the
pinned one
you know when you find people that you
can relate to and that you work well
with
and you don't worry about who's in cover
you're living a life that is true to
yourself you're
not playing these games and which you're
only talking to people because their
level
of power you're not trying to move up
like a
desperate kind of person in the back of
a line to a concert
meanwhile you know there might be a much
better concert
with a much shorter mind that you can
get into right away and it'll be the
best show that you've ever seen
so many people are focused on this
centralization they're focused on
who has the power in the center of the
narrative well meanwhile
there are people that are doing things
that are so much more interesting
outside of that and if these are people
that you connect with
then work with them and build with them
and create civilization with them
so that's my my pin to tweet yep then to
one about the guys
who can't go to the store without
strategizing i know people like that
right
right so this is a lot of people i
am thinking of one guy specifically and
everything that he does is based on what
he's read in the art of war
and the 48 laws of power running i get
that these are important books that we
need to understand
to like survive this uh denim for wolves
you know
called uh america or um the world
depending on
where you're standing um but these
people often don't
do anything and the reason that they are
born you know and unfortunately
however we're ready not to get people to
do things but to give people advice for
how to do things but these people aren't
even doing anything
they're just sitting around strategizing
and accomplishing nothing at all yeah
i see that all time i see another
variant on that
uh two different variants on that one i
call it the philosopher fallacy
that they're gonna figure it all out
from the top done and deliver us a plan
how to remake society right
i've see we've seen that playbook before
nazism
and stalinism i don't think we need
either of those
and our world is way too complex and you
know my background is from complexity
science the santa fe
institute and elsewhere and one of the
things you learn when you study
complexity science
is frankly how little we know about
predicting how a social system will
unfold over time
so someone that you know sits on the
mountaintop philosophizing for 10 years
and comes down with a plan and tells us
all to do it you know tell them to stuff
it
right and then the other one one of my
current pet peeves is
people who fall into too much
introspection you know they
go down the spiritualism rabbit hole and
have fun talking to themselves but never
get around to talking to anybody else
yeah there's definitely a lot of i guess
you could call it fear
where people they just they view
themselves as these
grand strategists who sit around and
wait for other people to do things and
then kind of come in and
take power but what actually happens is
they get completely left
out um simply because they're just like
sitting around
and strategizing on what we need is
people to strategize collaboratively
with people who are doing things we
need strategy and we need action we need
both
you know when if all the people are
doing is sitting around on a discord
channel
you know talking about optics and none
of these people are doing anything like
how
are they any different from the people
they're complaining about
um you know if there's this um idea in
the west that i don't like i actually um
i believe it's an eastern idea and it's
about
um non-action and being the dominant
mode of
communication and um something about
like
non-action i forget the exact name of
the phrase
but i don't like how america a country
that was founded
on creation that was founded you know
we're frontiers right um
and we're builders you know and for us
to suddenly become
um you know just like these non-dubers
these these non-players um
npcs you know um whatever the latest
name is for them i think a lot of people
that only strategize but don't do
don't realize that they too are the npcs
you know they like to think of
themselves
as different um and i don't really think
they are
yeah i agree you know in fact at least
in my version of game b
one of the things about game b there's a
lot there is no canonical game b there
is no game b
org there's just various of us telling
our versions of the story
in my version of the story uh one of the
watch words is what i call
bias for action right wow everything
else being equal you can sit on your ass
you can go out and do something and i
can tell you which one i'll bet on in
terms of actually changing the world
right
i love that that i saw that in you
that's one reason i reached out to you i
saw you as a person who
they don't always succeed but you're
always doing something right
yeah and even if we don't succeed the
first or the second or a
third time we're gonna learn from our
failures
and then we will succeed eventually if
we just keep doing what we care about
and
we keep putting up their things that
matter to us
we learn we become more active we
figure it out you know um but we we are
people that do things
and there are many that do not
and i i just think
that people have become meek and docile
in america and i i don't know if it's
like um like
this new kind of influence of uh
maybe like more eastern thought um where
it's like
you just need to sit there you know and
wait for things to happen
and um like okay i get that if you want
an easy life then you don't have a lot
of
passion or desire in you to really
affect anything
um but that's just not my sale i'm
an american who likes doing things i'm
an american who likes building i believe
that ambition is good
and i don't like that people shame each
other for ambition and that could
segue into my third tweet about
narcissism and shaming and how that
creates a village of idiots a lot of
people
are considered to be the the term that a
lot of these
you know like irony bros like to throw
around
is lacking self-awareness
and they're just really focused on how
other people lack self-awareness which
which to me
is ironic because they don't
have the self-awareness that all they do
is complain about other people
lacking self-awareness um so you got
these people with no self-awareness
complaining about how other people
don't have self-awareness because they
take themselves too seriously how dare
you not make an ironic joke how dare you
have a serious discussion
why why so serious you're not fun i'm so
they get shamed for being narcissistic
even if they're not
um the actual definition of narcissist
is being extremely fixated on oneself
and
one ego taking yourself seriously does
not mean you're narcissist it just means
maybe you're just uh different from
people in this generation right
um so these people get shamed for taking
themselves too seriously they get called
narcissists and then
they become clowns you know because they
get shamed so
they start turning everything into a
joke you know you can see it in the the
joker movie a lot of
that rhetoric is alluded to um and yeah
it creates a village of idiots and what
we need
is multiple villages of people who can
take themselves seriously that doesn't
mean they can't have fun or
tell jokes but it means there should be
like a basic civil
communication in which people can take
things seriously i mean and not be
labeled as
narcissists and shamed for it it's like
that the more you want to talk about a
serious idea the more likely
somebody is to just like shame you for
it
and um yeah i don't want to have a
village of idiots
yeah and yeah i got to tell you there
are a lot of these people out here who
you know i i at least complain about
their perspective as a post-modernist
essentially
where ideas aren't to be taken seriously
and everything is to be
subverted and there may be times for
that kind of critique might be useful to
find problems in existing structures but
it does not strike me as the way we
build what comes
next right you can't make fun of
everybody who's seriously trying to
build what comes next and actually get
there and i will say that's one of the
things i like a lot about our game b
community well we have many perspectives
from far
right to far left into directions that
neither right nor
left describes accurately yet we're all
serious
players we all think that we're doing
something that's important for the
future of humanity
and nobody undermines anybody for you
know engaging ideas seriously
and doing serious work and i think
you're absolutely right
yeah so let's move on to the next topic
one thing i was a little surprised i've
read some of your stuff from time to
time but i didn't quite realize how deep
you had gone
into the neo-reactionary side of things
here's a actual quote from you from one
of your writings
i was an early adopter of
neo-reactionary philosophy
propelled into the discourse by
accelerationist philosopher nick
land alongside political strategist
curtis yarbin
my purpose for exploring what struck me
is i'll be honest
a fringe community of dark triad
lunatics was
cultural my goal was to usher in a new
metaphysical current that i dubbed the
art right before i get into
the details of your travels in
neo-reactionary land
first i gotta ask how did a nice
progressive jewish girl like you get
drawn to the right
well i'm definitely not progressive
because of what progressives turned into
maybe i'm like a classical progressive
or something like that um but it was
because i was interested in
having real discussions people in the
neoliberal norms
of society were not able to be honest
with each other
they were just focused on pr
they didn't see what was really on their
mind and um you know for
new reaction for me was just like me
talking to a few people on twitter
really early on in the game i talked
about this on the justin murphy show it
wasn't like i wanted to join
you know like some some like right
movement or something it was just like
these are people that i can have honest
discussions with
i like that we can be honest with each
other um and it was a fringe
community of dark triad lunatics um i
am very fascinated with dark triad
personalities and i think there's a lot
that can be
learned from dark triad personalities
and i have a few
dark triad personalities myself it
matches
majority of neo-reactionary people which
is why i
publicly exited the movement um a lot of
these people are just like straight-up
sociopaths um
but for for me this is the i guess the
battle and maybe for a lot of other
women who are
what i would consider like dark
philosophers um i call this philosopher
queens
now is like how do we meet people that
we can have discussions with on darker
issues without running into people who
don't like us simply because we like
have to choose or
you know are jewish or just like a
little weird you know like how can we
have
discussions on dark and difficult issues
with people
who are not nasty you know um
and i'm like well i have a problem i'm
going to create a solution
elixir swan is one of the solutions i'm
just building a community of people that
could have interesting discussions that
i could be real with
that were also um you know not
um you know uh near reactionaries so
um yeah how i have you know reaction
it's something
that i explore because i wanted
interesting people to talk to
i do not endorse it um but there are
some good ideas that were proposed um
like exit over
voice being a big one you know which is
close to the
game b theory that you have and close to
the pulling out of the narrative idea
it is simply building alternative
nations alternative societies
alternative industries um you can read
on the diamond age by neil stevenson
you know you you create different um
even temporary autonomous zones
where people can live in their own way
you have alternative competing
governments
to the main government right um why have
one government in america when we can
have 50 right let
left 50 governments bloom i did a little
bit of reading in
menchus mold bugs uh writings that was
curtis's
political moniker and you know while i
found it kind of
it was intricate and well and deeply
thought out at the end of the day i said
you know this guy's just a
monarchist feudalist not the kind of
person that
i would react to their politics
correctly not what i'm looking for for
the future
but i will say i have interacted a bit
with curtis yarvin in real life
in his role on the urban project oh okay
yeah i have a few friends that work at
urban and i also
don't agree with yarvin's philosophies
um
i mean the article that you quoted from
was actually me critiquing
mulberry himself um mr yarvin you know
he's um
he's like one of those all strategy
people um but if at least he is
taking action but there are a lot of
fans of his
that are just about the the optics
chatter that don't get anything done
um and i don't actually curtis isn't
involved in urban anymore from what i
understand
i i think that his problem is that he is
trying to become the
new machiavelli but he doesn't
understand
that in order to have a real influence
you need aesthetics
you need culture so it's kind of like
thank you curtis for
you know like writing your new version
of the prince
i'm excited to read it when it comes out
um but
nobody's ever gonna know who he is
outside of these little circles because
he doesn't really engage with culture he
doesn't really
engage with the the flow
the the pulse of humanity that's not the
same as the narrative the pulse of
humanity it's almost
like an evolian kind of it's a higher
force or so a lot a lot of catholics
could allude to to this it's an inner
power you know um of passionate people
who who have the this horse inside of
them you could say
um i noticed in people like you um caleb
you know it's
this is important to have um and i think
that people like curtis
don't want it to exist because they kind
of just want to control everything
um so yeah i mean i
i think that like having that verse of
power that
that inspires you you know some might
see as like some type of divinity others
might see
some type of delusion on whatever it is
we need to
understand it before we go on actually i
forgot to ask you this question before
my audience isn't necessarily up on all
the buzzwords around this stuff what is
the dark triad frankly i'm not 100
sure myself okay so the dark chart is uh
three personality traits there is
machiavellianism
there is psychopathy and there is
neuroticism
and we actually i might have the third
one wrong it's been a
while since i've like really delved into
dark triad i'm
narcissism machiavellianism and
psychopathy
so um yeah these are the three traits
that apparently
make you very hard to work with um
there's something of of that sword i'm
because there's so much volatility
you know there's so much infighting you
have i'm the biggest god in the room no
i'm the biggest god i'm the ruler of
hell i'm the monarch of insert company
here and
you know it's actually much better to to
be the meanest person in the room and
work with nice
people that you don't need to be worried
about screwing you over
you know um because if it's just like a
den of wolves
the wolves are going to eat each other
yeah and it's not the right way to go
forward i just had a really wonderful
two podcast series with tyson yonka
porta
recently which we'll have published
right before this one or a couple weeks
before this one comes out
and in that he basically said that the
original sin of mankind
which he called which he labeled he's an
indigenous australian person and but
also
a scholar of complexity science which
made for a fascinating conversation
uh that in the indigenous perspective
the downfall of
mankind is narcissism the belief that i
am better than you without any reason
other than
i said so and that sounds like it's part
of this dark triad
i gotta say i don't think those are the
kind of people that are gonna build the
future i certainly hope not in fact in
the other part of this dark triad thing
you mentioned is uh sociopathy
uh you know one of one of our key
analysis is that power attracts
sociopaths
in my working days i was involved at
pretty high levels in corporate america
wall street i even worked in the white
house for a little while and
my perspective is that the sea levels of
larger american corporations probably 10
of the people are sociopaths and that is
not good
in our game b world one of the things
we're always on the lookout is how do we
build in
institutional structures such that
sociopaths
are not pulled to the levers of power
and part of part of the way to do that
is by having less levers of power
but instead are routed to where they may
actually be useful you know
frankly yeah now sociopaths probably
good as a warrior right you want someone
to just go out go out there and kill
right but a sociopath is a leader no
thank you very much so i would say if
you
run into a philosophy or an organization
where you're seeing
sociopaths and positions of power run
don't walk would be my recommendation
and i would also add learn from them um
and there was an article i wrote
at trigger warnings several years ago um
2016 actually it's called the sociopaths
coma and i work to deconstruct
sociopathy for what it is and
the conclusion that i came to is that
sociopaths
are bound by their puppet master reality
titles and they can't imagine a world in
which they are not pulling the strings
so um i don't know if you know about
neural linguistic programming i'm sure
you do actually
you know about the the law of requisite
variety right the more options you have
the more moves you can make
you know i have intentionally not dug
into the kind of the pop culture
linguistic programming stuff it looked
to me a neuro-linguistic program it
looked at me a little bit like a
packaged
cult kind of thing but i do know a lot
about cognitive neuroscience so i may be
able to
to react to some not to the packaged pop
culture nlp thing
okay yeah and then if you know a lot
about cognitive neuroscience nlp will
seem like a joke to you um to other
people it's a way of life um it's about
mirroring people
finding their dominant senses like if
somebody says
i see that this is something that's
really interesting then you want to like
speak to them
and you know i'm visual metaphors or
somebody's like i heard you and then you
want to respond to them
in a you know auditory way to get their
to gain their dominant sense so you can
um
build rapport with them um or claim
however them depending on how you want
to look at it
um but what i noticed i'm about the law
of requisite variety which
simply means that the more options you
have the more moves you can make that
this is a game
that initially it seems rigged in favor
of this sociopath
because they're not bound by emotional
reactions they don't have moralistic
impulses
they are not stuck in this human
cognition frame they
can do horrible things and not feel bad
about it
and they don't they don't experience
emotion um
but then i started to think about it
more they don't have the visceral
passion that's only possible in people
who aren't like that so
even though they can imitate emotion
they know
they're missing a human core and people
they can tell that they're a bit too
perfect
you know they don't possess the capacity
to display emotional
weakness or emotional strength because
they don't experience it so this is
where
sociopaths are at a disadvantage because
they
don't have the capacity to show that
are humans with emotions um the best
thing they can
do is mimicry that that's all they're
capable of is
is mimicry um they're trapped in a
modality of superficial
perfection um and they also can't build
any rapport with people who recognize
them for an actor they conceal their
flaws
to such a point of dull emptiness that
it's just like
obviously you know this is a wolf in
sheep's clothing um
i've often described as a highly
conscientious person
who is excessively civil you know um
these are the people
that we need to watch out for we have
the scapegoats the designated villains
the uh
you know bad guys of the world that are
constantly getting articles written
about how bad they are
um but the worst people are the ones
that pretend to
be nice guys and those are the real
sociopaths um
so my solution about the sociopath
problem
is that we should have complete mastery
over them
so and this is back to what you were
talking about how social hops could be
useful
you know um but we can mimic the games
of puppet mastery we can
explore the modality of sociopathy but
it's still a coma
right it's somewhat exciting and
entertaining but it's really
debilitating
in terms of emotional or moral strategy
so they lack the tools
to connect with other people in a true
meaningful way
so what we should do is have complete
mastery over them themselves i mean
we're treating them how they treat
others
we might as well respect it we should
use sociopaths associated fast few other
people
sociopaths should become our personal
play things um and this is how
i see the the way to solve this is to
have sociopaths r play things
understanding them
like they understand other humans feed
them at their own game
and learn from them learn how to be a
moral
emotional person who understands how to
be a sociopath when you
need to as long as you don't hurt
anybody i guess you you call me a
libertarian um
i i believe in the nap non-aggression
principle as long as you don't hurt
anybody
i think what you're doing is fine um so
yeah it's important to learn from bad
people but not become like them but
understand
what their tactics are and i would say
that this is the best solution that i've
come up with we can't just you know
get rid of all the sociopaths so
great because you'd say again where that
article is that is an article that is of
interest to our people in our community
the issue of how to deal with sociopaths
where can we find that
you can find it on trigger warning um
it's down right now i'll type it into
the chat i mean it's not down like you
can still read the articles um but we're
currently on hiatus because we're
pivoting trigger warning injury brand
um but yeah that is one of the articles
there
okay got it we'll put it on our if it's
available i'll put it up on our
episode page as we will all the links of
things that we talked about
well that's actually a good transition
to my next topic
which is you know you i think currently
still position yourself
as someone who's interested in the new
artwrite you wrote a book by that title
and you talk about it from time to time
what is the new art right and i know it
has to do with aesthetics
but why don't you just go with that and
then i'll get into some questions about
the book itself
sure the new writer is the name of my
book it's a current that i created
for people to build a new aesthetic
movement quite simply
the conservative mainstream right and
the
alt-right are just as bad as the social
justice
left to me so we need to create options
where creative people
are able to communicate build and
produce
without being targeted by social justice
mobs
and without being annoyed by like
bonehead you know like ultra america
first
types you know what i mean so to be
needed and aren't right full of creative
people that are unbound
by the social justice political correct
narrative
we need to be building our own
institutions building our own theater
scenes
we need to be building our own companies
and doing it with our own ethos and um
just to be clear
like i'm not a traditional right-winger
in any way
my social views are pretty center-left
um and economically i'm a centerist at
this point if you can believe it i'm a
radical centrist right um
but there is like a metaphysical realm
you know on the right that i find a lot
more interesting um that's how i got
into
philosophers like evola on spindler and
megan
and like even more you know um
canceled philosophers like yagi um not
not because i
like agreed with what they're saying but
because i enjoyed exploring
that current um i i dubbed the
term psychic fascism um which is being
able to explore fascism
without advocating for a fascist
government or being a fascist yourself
letting your mind wander
now i'm not sure i get my head around
that when i think of fascists i think
enemies of civilization yeah yeah i know
that that's
okay that's what i mean is like that is
exactly what they are
but if we have like a more psychic form
of that where people are exploring dark
areas of their mind and not
hurting people okay if we have people
that are engaged
you know in artistic projects on like
for example a guy he
makes a painting that is extremely uh
offensive but it's also beautiful and
provocative you know um
he's not actually you know advocating
for a fascist government but he
is you know like displaying imagery that
really
breaks down borders and boundaries of
people's minds he's making them think of
a new way
um this is why i'm really big against
censorship of the arts
um because i think people need to to see
it all the good and
bad and the ugly and i think that they
are right should be a community of
creatives that
are willing to think as extreme as
they can that are also creating things
but that are not
you know advocating for fascist
government or hurting each other so i
hope that clarifies things for you
that helps a little bit let me just push
back a little bit you know i think about
movements that for which aesthetics were
significant
some of them aren't such good ones right
you think of nazi aesthetics
kind of a weird mix of german
romanticism realism and grieco
roman classicism and you think of the
stalinist
socialist realism that actually were
taken quite seriously by those regimes
but then we look at other revolutions
that were mostly benevolent and benign
and good from society the american
revolution
and the british glorious revolution of
i would say neither of those had an
aesthetic component they were
essentially just
continued on in the way of their
societies with respect to aesthetics so
from that those samplings of history
might we say that
trying to combine aesthetics with
revolution might not be a good thing
yeah i mean obviously like the the
hitler example is obvious
um if you've seen the movie max it's
about hitler as an art school student
and he makes very bad paintings that
nobody likes um and then he
makes some paintings of the third reich
and his art teacher says this is the
most incredible work of art i've ever
seen
i mean it's a really good movie because
it shows how aesthetics and politics can
get convoluted
and suddenly you have a horrific
group of actual fascists right um but
you know like you can say that you like
uh you know like nancy uniforms or nazi
architecture
and be really against nazism um there's
no reason you can't um
like uh brutalist architecture it has
fascist connotations
um and then you have like the the
italian fascists they were
futurists first and the italian
futurists were
an art movement of people like us who
talked about difficult issues that
others were
afraid of addressing and they wrote i
don't know if you've read the futurist
manifesto
but i really really like this kind of
expression what i don't like is to see
violence what i don't like is to see
people get hurt what i don't like is
this the authoritarian government
but do i want to see brilliant people
that have
dark ideas collaborate artistically
absolutely
okay i guess i can go with that but
again
i would you know at least from my
perspective think that what this
alt-right in particular is
suggesting is the exact opposite of what
we need for our society
on the other hand i'm with you i don't
have any use for the politically correct
social justice warriors either right
we really need to do is create a space
for sensible people to create a better
future for us all
what uh let's dig in a little bit into
the new art write the book one of the
essays i thought was
interesting i'd love to get your
thoughts on what you were trying to get
at here
it was called fighting words to be
precise and
kind of the core of it was 10 tips for
successful counter-revolution
what were you trying to get at there i
was making fun of listicles
at the time there were a lot of really
dumb buzzfeed top 10 lists coming out
and they were just so ridiculous so i
decided i was going to
mock them and come up with 10 tips for
the counter revolution
you know um it was silly you know take
it with a grain of salt
this is one of the less serious pieces
in the new right right
um listicles are dumb might as well make
a funny one i mean that was what went
into
my head when i i wrote that on but there
are a few successful
tips in there um like you know make
friends get out of the house
you know don't sit around complaining
about how the left is winning
you know do something yourself that's
going to live an impact um don't
don't be a victim be a winner not a
minor you know like if you're just some
guy complaining about white genocide
how are you different from the anti-fuzz
you know how are you different from the
protests
groups you're doing the same thing as
them so
yeah if it's a satirical issue but there
were some
some nuggets of truth in there if you
know what i mean yeah there was one i
found it was kind of interesting i'm not
trying to
100 understood it but maybe i got a
sense of it which was except that the
right wing is the proletariat
yeah so this was written in 2014
to be clear um and it was at a time
where
the left um and i was still pretty much
a leftist at the time i mean i'm i'm
still the
leftist accordion so some people um but
there are also people that think i'm
a new nutsy myself so who knows um but
it was really just the
realization that i had um that a lot of
the anti-pc left is starting to have now
is that the left is the elite um not
that everybody on the left is an elite
um but the democratic party is a party
of elites
and the republican party is the
the um the unwashed masses the right has
become the new proletariat
there's no room left on the left that is
how i like to put it
that sounds like that's a lot of your
reaction against the left which causes
you to use at least right terminology
that you don't believe there's room for
real discourse on the left anymore
yeah yeah there's definitely not um and
i
like like i said i'm not like the right
winger or anything
um my idea um for the art rate is kind
of like to vanguard the alt-right into
something that is more about creation
self-expression
just being oneself and doing cool things
essentially
you know um and to do your own thing
you you might not be able to do that on
the left anymore so what what you see
is really brilliant people philosophers
scientists engineers that would have
been left
10 years ago um but now because the left
has become so elitist
and the right house has become the
proletariat these people are kind of
like shoved into the right
it's a disturbing phenomena you know um
because i grew up
pretty attached to the loft i believed
in human rights and i was
anti-censorship i was anti-globalization
but now all of these things are
apparently right-wing um
so who knows i mean these labels are are
so stupid and that's why the new art
write is about
just transcending that whole thing and
subverting it and creating
uh a better a game b of my own you know
yeah exactly i was going to say i think
it sounds like your heart is more as a
game b person than as an alt-righter
right
just to be clear i was never an
all-writer
i was an alternative writer because i i
write cool things um
but no i i was never sorry um i
i was never on the already in any shape
or form
that's a good pun though i like that an
alt writer right with a w
right yeah yeah um so i i never
liked the people with low iqs that
attacked people for their appearances
um like these are anti-semitic
misogynistic
very mean people and there's absolutely
no reason to
be associated with the all right at all
um and if
i hear somebody think that i'm already
like i just laugh because they all read
has been so
nasty to me like they've taught me every
name in the book i'm so no i'm not
alright i was i was a target of deal
right because i was just a weird
intellectual doing my own thing
um so um but i i will say
that i believe that a lot of the
outright just comes from alienation from
society
these people they don't fit in um in the
mainstream they feel
unwelcome in public institutions and
they feel like they just need a
community you know they feel like they
just
need a community a lot of these people
are young and they they feel like they
can't discuss the real views
um with their peers their parents i mean
i had a friend of mine
um a pretty you know centrist
you know center left friend who
was telling me he told me that he was
afraid of getting doxxed
because of his views i'm like you're
like the leftist
like why are you afraid of getting ducks
and it's like well my friend just got
talked and you know people are
getting really mad because they don't
like my opinions i'm like you were like
the most militars
you know like if you're afraid of
getting dogs like i think we we have a
climb out of fear you know yeah and i
will say this is something that's ugly
uh in our society and it's why you know
my own view is both fuck both the right
and the left neither of them struck me
as
what's useful and they're both turning
vicious against each other right
as you said you've been attacked in bad
ways by all rights and
probably by some of the lefties too yeah
i've been attacked by by the anti-fuzz
they decided it was funny to dox me i
mean
they said and i quote like how can you
say
that she's not a nazi she stated here
that she wanted to change the outright
into some
gothic horseshit i think that was like
the way they actually used
um something like saman vanguard got the
horseshit
and that was what they thought that i
thought that the art rate was no like
the art rate is like five
by neo-nazis we're gonna do our own
thing here and you guys
can stay over there you know like
getting arrested
at marches but we're going to build
empires of the mind
you know because that's what we do with
philosophers
yep i guess but i would i just my advice
i'd say call us something besides the
all
the the art right because yeah i guess
people are gonna see that with me they
all right now
um i really i hope they don't though
because like nobody that knows me
ever thought of that um they could see
that it was actually like an overthrow
of the outright that it was like we were
looking to replace
the alt-right with the art right we we
were
deliberately gentrifying
the all right that was exactly what we
wanted to do
that was the plan yeah i guess i was you
know having watched your tweets over the
months i was a little surprised to
discover that you had
you know as i said flirted with the neo
reaction but now i understand that
you're kind of a
zeitgeist surfer looking for interesting
and peculiar things to riff off of
right yeah also just a fiercely
independent thinker who does
not believe that enforcing social norms
on
what you can think is a good idea yeah
anyone knows me and it was pretty hard
for anyone to get to put their social
norms on me either right
take your special norms off my body
exactly
another interesting essay in the book
was called new institution
yeah and you mentioned the h.l menken
conference in baltimore
that you'd attended and i had to smile
and laugh i've read every book
h.l menken has written including ones
that are almost impossible to get your
hands on
he is in a uh i have a library in my uh
in my apartment in town
i'm trying to get the box set i love
that box that i'm trying to get my hands
on it yeah but i got mostly
old antique copies of stuff you know
stuff from the 30s and the 20s
i even have his hl menkin baby book
which is
ascending where he actually for money
wrote a book on
how uh mothers should take care of young
babies
you have like obscure yeah this is like
talking to friends about like they have
like a
limited edition vinyl you know this is
great exactly
yeah this is the ancient stuff but
anyway i thought it was an interesting
point
i loved um notes and democracy it was
just a really good book
you know i just but the way that he
views the world is similar to
the way that i view the world um it's
more like a
like um nietzsche or like sterner it's
individualist
you know um or even like um like the
junior concept of the anarch
you know like the self-serving
individual
that does things for their own reasons
not for the reasons of the
community not for the reasons of the the
government but just because they want to
do them you know complete
freedom of action you know that one book
i do not have
is menken's translation of nietzsche
menkin wrote the very first
translation of nietzsche into english in
1909 when he was like 19 years old
and it's very clear that menken is a
nietzsche
kind of character but yeah there's an
awful lot of interesting stuff in making
but on the other hand he has uh
you know a dark side too and you know
i've also read his diaries which were
released
i don't know 20 years ago excerpts from
them yeah
and wow they're very interesting but
it's also pretty damn clear
he was a pretty bad anti-semite that's
worth knowing as well
i actually i did not know that i've only
read notes on democracy
i just saw him as like an individual
standard case i thought he was like a
nietzschean like a sterner
type um he is mostly but he's a guy from
that era
from the south more or less baltimore
was sort of a southern town
and so he had that old boy anti-semitism
in a pretty nasty fashion
but he didn't seem to let it affect his
personal life his business partner was
jewish his publisher was jewish he got
along fine with jewish people but he
does
have an ugly anti-semitic streak in it
that he cannot be denied
but on the other hand he's an
interesting writer so i wouldn't i would
say i'm not going to cancel him i'm not
going to pull down his statue
i'm not going to get rid of my my h.l
menken library i'm going to acknowledge
that he was
one of the more brilliant thinkers of
the early part of the 20th century
but he had a flaw he was an anti-semite
so
yeah you want to throw the baby out with
the bath water and
um is a jewish woman who has interacted
in right-wing intellectual
circles um i've actually attempted to
dissect anti-semitism and figure out
what it's about um you know and i i
would like to understand it and one of
the conclusions that i came to is that
it's about fear of the other
you know um also like a fear of
neuroticism
this is a big one um a simple
distaste for people who
might not have like the perfect
um like level of kanji consciousness you
know what what i mean
there definitely seems to be like a a
bit of a hatred for the other
and um and then the other dissection i
made of anti-semitism
was that it was just um like the far
right scapegoat
was the jews um but what they really
meant was like the
global corporations doing trade that
were like affecting
nations ability to thrive um but they
didn't
say that they said the jews um when
maybe a lot of the grievances were
simply
like global corporations um but you know
you see you have a problem with global
corporations people think you're an
anti-semite then some people jump how
high
i mean it's complicated you know yeah on
the other hand to me it's a signal when
people start talking about
the jews to just realize that there's
something seriously wrong with their
world model
right yeah you know you know i love the
quote somewhere that
what is it that anti-semitism is the
bigotry of idiots
something like that and you know it's a
very good warning sign for people if
you're involved in a community where
people start talking about the jews
just head for the door right and you'll
be better off for it right
yeah i mean like there was a time when i
tried to argue with them
and i said well look there are a lot of
jews that don't believe in global
corporatism you know there are a lot of
jews that
have no media power um but i realized
like these people were they were gonna
hate the jews no matter what
exactly i mean i didn't want to be what
was it um they're shell of metal there's
actually a name
um for like the one jew that's like
accepted by the nazis i'm kind of like
the uncle tom's there's also the shuttle
of metals
and i'm like i don't want to be a shadow
of metal like i'm just an independent
thinker
who wants to live my own life and build
cool things and talk to people who
interest me um so um yeah like hatred of
the other is bad um and i do think that
a lot of it comes from that and um
like i said um a lot of it comes from um
a racism related to neurobiology
um there are a lot of people that think
personality traits are hardwired you
know you've got the big five personality
test
um and some people just happen to be a
little lower in congenitalism
a little higher on neuroticism and you
know if you have a problem with somebody
because they're weird
you know which i think a lot of
anti-semitism is just like a hatred of
being weird
right um then the problem is you the
problem is that you are a
boring person who does not understand
life um and that that's their loss
that would agree i agree let's go on to
talk about another essay
what's so bad about cosmopolitanism oh
yeah the provocative title
yeah what were you getting out there
okay so
in the nationalist community people
scapegoat cosmic holidays and
they say zoom cosmopolitan bohemian
mercies
um but cosmopolitan
wasn't always a way for people to like
dominate you through marxism um it was
simply a way for people to
explore all types of life to travel
through different countries to learn uh
about how different people lived um
and cosmopolitanism was
a pursuit of knowledge it was the
pursuit
of culture of learning of experience
but now the way that that people use the
term
they're they're talking more about we
have a certain type of like
bohemian intellectual that they
personally do not like
um and i don't think that's the right
way
to go about it i mean first of all if
you really wanted to you could become a
cosmopolitan nationalist there's no
reason you can't support national
borders and
also like the idea of traveling and
meeting new people
i mean that there's nothing
contradictory about that i think a lot
of people
they just don't understand nuance and to
them like anything cosmopolitan
or anything like marxists is bad
to them i'm even anything you know
creatives is bad to them this is why the
the nazis burnt
the books if they're more interesting
philosophers um and this is
also why there was there the nazi purge
you know the night of the long knives
you know a lot of the
um early nazis that were called
strasseris
you know they were considered to be like
a degenerate because they were gay and
creative um so most people don't even
know that they think there's like only
one nazi party
they don't even know that there was
actually like a
split and that the um more
creative nazis got got killed you know
during during that historical night
um but of course i wasn't there you know
in history
you know we have the the news um and the
news is just like a d
based version of history so we don't
know what really happened um
but what what i will say is that we
should always question everything that
we're told
and form our own conclusions yeah that's
a that's always a good idea i didn't
you know you mentioned the strassers you
know people don't as you said most
people don't know about that ancient
history but
you know nazi was national socialist
there actually were socialists
in the national socialists and the
strasser brothers were more or less the
leaders of that faction and that was
another reason they were kicked out and
i think one of them was killed in the
night of the long knives so
a lot of oddities in the in that history
so basically you're you come out in
favor of cosmopolitan again i'd say
that's uh not very compatible with
today's uh
right wing to say the least right yeah
and again
this is why i'm using the turmeric right
because i'm saying you guys are doing
something
that i am not interested but i'm
interested in doing is
over here you know got it
so the final essay i think it was
actually an appendix or something
which more or less summed up where you
were coming from it was called
toward a dark bohemia tell us about that
yeah so the dark bohemia is what i
envision is
in your terms there would be like a game
b for the newer right
which is a world in which people
can live together creatively where
people can express themselves
where they can have a good time have
intellectual conversations where they
can engage in
theater philosophy the arts um almost
like a symposium
that becomes movement that is the the
dark leukemia people
exploring the darker areas of
consciousness
having an experience in which they're
not confounded by
reason and rationality
they're they're not a part of this the
opiate of the masses right reason is an
opiate
of the masses but it's still a preferred
toll of control
among the elite you know it's kind of
like a materialist prison
right so um while we do need reason you
know like as an enlightened society
what we don't need is reason turning
into a part of this neoliberal
monolithic game culture
so what's the answer you create a dark
bohemia
you know you create a world where we
have a
fiery new metapolitical current right
um and we engage in
everything from having fashion shows to
having live bands play that have this
really dark and powerful energy you know
um
and we didn't have to do this in a way
that's like uh what some people might
say it's satanic um no
it's just exploring darker topics and
exploring darker ideas in a really
creative way
even poetry you know art
um even just getting on stage in a
costume and giving a
powerful speech that is the dark
bohemian people
uniting to form this new
um this new game i'll call it um game
dirk bohemia
yeah um so that's uh it's a bit of a
romantic essay i'm
i'm not gonna deny that um but i i think
it is important to understand how reason
um and utilitarianism and i know
spangler talked a lot
about this um are are being used to kind
of like take the the soul
out of people and turn them into like
these these non-player
characters and i think that we need to
fight that by creating a
resurrection of philosophy yeah i think
that's a that is a good vision you know
it does oftentimes feel like game a is a
flat land that has lost its soul
we're all driven by this machine to
maximize money on money return
and there and whatever beauty and
conviviality
exists kind of seems to exist almost
despite
the the behemoth itself and if we
started to think about what does a
society look at look like where
these kinds of uh aesthetic and personal
and
uh particularly in my mind convivial the
idea of
you know celebration with other people
face to face
in song and dance and drink and maybe
some other crazy stuff
right that made that central to our
society rather than money on money
return
would be heading towards on a better
road for sure i would like to see that
and
i don't think money is the problem that
a lot of people on the left
do i'm a lot of these anti-capitalists
are kind of um
they don't understand that the core
issue is the utilitarian
lack of interest in things that really
blow people's minds
um it's more of like an interest in just
like sticking to
what they consider to be the most
efficient
thing but they're what they do when they
do that
is they lock out new possibilities and
they actually become less efficient
as a result because they cut out
anything in the margins
you know that might like temporarily
create
a bit too much entropy but if all
they're doing is waiting out entropy
you know then they're basically weeding
out growth
and it's not that entropy is good but
entropy is real
entropy exists and maybe instead of like
weeding out entropy we should find out
how to
to scale it properly um i have a model i
call it scaling volatility where if you
scale
volatility positively then you have
vitality
um but if you schedule utility
negatively and then you
have decline um it's important to
understand that entropy is a force that
you don't just have to run away from
you can learn the edges of it you can
explore entropy and like figure out the
way to make it work
best for you but unfortunately the
majority of people are just like oh no
entropy and then they think that they're
like making progress when they're
actually like
holding back the evolution of um the
species and of civilization
got it that's an interesting vision uh
let's see what else we got here a few
things left to go you've talked about
from time to time
about anarchy what are your thoughts on
on anarchy as an alternative
well i always considered myself an
anarchist because i didn't believe in an
authoritarian role and i believed in the
sovereignty of the individual
um but you know a lot of anarchists
they've called me some not nice names um
i found myself more like on the sterner
you know individualist anarchist side of
things um i remember taking a lot of
flack because i
i worked for an anti-ipc anarchist site
called attack the system
you know which i mean i i don't even
know if i would be
an anarchist like according to like the
terms
of what anarchy means now um
romeo is always about self-sovereignty
so you know people are like oh seared
libertarian um
i've made the joke that a libertarian is
just an anarchist that gets
wise to success so um
yeah yeah that's how i feel about that
all righty now as a strong woman who's
uh in you know sailed in many different
seas
i'd love to get your thoughts on sex
gender and all that
i think the sex and gender are talked
about too much
and there's a big over importance placed
on them whether we're talking
about sexual adventures that people have
like on their blogs
you know like i don't want to read about
it sorry um you know like
i want to do it with my girlfriend and
you know um
i don't i don't want to read these you
know like vice articles about
somebody's sexual charade i think that
there's too much information out about
it you know i i find it to be a
kind of um i don't want to say
degenerate right um but
uh classless you know it's it's vulgar
um so yeah like have the best sex that
you can
but like do you really have to announce
it all the time like whether you're on
like an insult complaining about how you
can't have sex or like a sex worker
talking about how sex work is like the
best thing in the world or like
just some horny guy who's talking about
like how many times got laid it's like
aren't you guys gonna talk about
something more interesting than
sex or aren't you like sex is sacred to
me sex is sacred and it should be kept
private so
um that is my view on sex um my view on
gender
is that i really do not care um i
am bisexual you know i'm so i like men i
like women
i like who i like i i don't really care
about all the gender wars i don't um
have a problem with trans people um
the trans friends that i have have told
me they have a problem with like the
weaponizing of
transgenderism as like a political cause
um and they they don't support like um
counseling people for using the wrong
pronouns they think that's stupid and
they say
they say fuck pronouns and these are
like trans friends of mine
so um i think a lot of it is overblown
in the media what happens is um
you know people that they magnify like
the really you know deranged
you know pronoun police and and they
make you think that like all trans
people are like that when they're not
and i also just think that there are
more important issues like i don't care
if somebody is trans it doesn't matter
to me
like i i just don't care um
sure i'd like to see an end to pronoun
policing um it goes overboard on
when you have like a poor white working
class construction worker who just uses
the wrong program and suddenly he lost
he lost his job because he didn't have
the education to know what the
the pronoun was it's a horrible thing
when that happens um but there's no
reason not to be respectful to people
and refer to them as their preferred
pronouns um
i i just don't care so much to me this
is like really mundane to be honest
gotcha all right that sounds uh you know
i understand where you're coming from
there
and finally something you tweeted about
recently or retweeted i think actually
the recent slate star codex controversy
where
for those those folks who aren't
following this this is a uh
a blog and i would call it the
rationalist tradition in fact i believe
the
author originally started writing on les
wrong which is
one of the core rationalist blogs
and he was being interviewed by the new
york times and the new york times
was going to publish a story but
insisted on using his real name
and for various reasons he thought he
could be a victim of the
online mobs and said that if they went
ahead and did that he'd take his
blog down and he did yeah yeah it's a
shame scott is a prolific blogger
and doxing people is horrible you should
never do that
i mean the thing is like he is actually
a good guy
like when i was going through some
serious trauma he referred me to
a professional like scott is a pillar in
the rationalist community he has never
said or done anything racist um he even
wrote like an anti-neo-reactionary
faq you know he does not agree with any
of that stuff um
so i really i have no idea i'm not like
a rationalist insider
um i have rationalist friends um but i
like to explore rationality
as an artist um i i don't know if the
new york times article is even going to
come out and i'm like we're talking
about earlier i don't care about the new
york times i'm never going to get a job
there
so um i don't know i mean journalists
are bullies
i mean they do go after easy targets
it's possible that scott is autistic
and maybe didn't realize that like
something in his blog
that he said could be interpreted as
racist like i
i really don't know um i hate these
witch hunts like i hate the way these
journalists do this um
and it's because they're not going after
the real bad guys they're not going
after like
the true evil people you know like the
wolves and sheep's clothing
who pretend to to be uh you know saints
you know that the most evil people in
the world are not gonna act
like the villains um but instead these
activists and journalists
they go after innocent people who were
actually like pillars of our communities
um and i i think they should stop and
hopefully they they get pushed back from
this whole incident yep i think that's
uh i would agree with you on that
well rachel i think this has been a very
interesting conversation we've covered
all kinds of ground
uh i learned a bunch of things while i
was doing the research for it i
really like to thank you for coming on
the show yeah yeah it was fun
i'm happy to talk in the future and yeah
i hope to see you at the
elixir salon okay we'll see if we can
make it well
thanks again rachel very good awesome
take care
[Music]
production services and audio editing by
jared janes consulting
music by tom muller at modern space
music dot com